Funding for this program is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...
Supporting space for the future
Now we turn to the hardest philosopher
we're going to read in this course.
Today we turn to the hardest philosopher
Let's turn to Immanuel Kant, who offers a different account
of why we have a categorical
duty to respect the dignity of persons
and not to use people as means merely,
even for good ends.
Kant excelled at the University of
Konigsberg at the age of 16.
At the age of 31, he got his
first job as an unsalaried lecturer paid on commission,
based on the number of students
who showed up at his lectures.
This is a sensible system that
Harvard would do well to consider.
Luckily for Kant, he was a
popular lecturer and also an industrious one,
and he was a very good lecturer.
He was a very good lecturer.
And so he eked out a meager living.
It wasn't until he was 57
that he published his first major work,
but it was worth the wait.
The book was The Critique of Pure Reason,
perhaps the most important work in all of modern philosophy.
And a few years later, Kant wrote
The Groundwork for the Metaphysics of Morals,
which we read in this course.
I want to acknowledge, even before we start,
that Kant is a difficult thinker.
But it's important to try
to figure out what he's saying,
because what this book is about is, well,
it's about what the supreme
principle of morality is, number one,
and it's also, it gives us an account,
one of the most powerful accounts we have,
of what freedom really is.
So,
let me start today.
Kant rejects utilitarianism.
He thinks that
the individual person,
all human beings,
have a certain dignity
that commands our respect.
The reason the individual is sacred,
and the individual is a
bearer of rights according to Kant,
doesn't stem from the idea that we own ourselves,
but instead from the idea
that we are all rational beings.
We're all rational beings, which simply means
that we are beings who are capable of reason.
We are also autonomous beings,
autonomous beings,
which is to say that we are
beings capable of acting and choosing freely.
Now, this capacity for reason and freedom
isn't the only capacity we have.
We also have the capacity for pain and pleasure,
for suffering and satisfaction.
Kant admits,
the utilitarians were
half right.
Of course,
we seek to avoid pain,
and we like pleasure.
Kant doesn't deny this.
What he does deny
is Bentham's claim
that pain and pleasure are our sovereign masters.
He thinks that's wrong.
Kant thinks
that it's our rational capacity that makes us distinctive,
that makes us special,
that sets us apart from and above mere animal existence.
It makes us something more
than just physical creatures with appetites.
Now,
we often think
of freedom as simply consisting
of doing what we want,
or in the absence of
obstacles to getting what we want.
That's one way of thinking about freedom.
But this isn't Kant's idea of freedom.
Kant has a more stringent, demanding notion
of what it means to be free.
And though it's stringent and
demanding, if you think it through,
it's actually pretty persuasive.
Kant reasons as follows.
When we, like animals,
seek after pleasure,
or the satisfaction of our
desires, or the avoidance of pain,
when we do that, we aren't really acting freely.
Why not?
We're really acting
as the slaves of those appetites and impulses.
I didn't choose
this particular hunger or that particular appetite.
And so when I act to satisfy it,
I'm just acting according to natural necessity.
And for Kant, freedom is the opposite of necessity.
There was an advertising slogan for the
soft drink Sprite a few years ago.
The slogan was,
Obey your thirst.
There's a Kantian insight buried
in that Sprite advertising slogan.
That, in a way, is Kant's point.
When you go for Sprite or Pepsi,
you're really, you might think that
you're choosing freely Sprite versus Pepsi,
but you're actually obeying something, a thirst.
Or maybe a desire manufactured or massaged by advertising.
You're obeying a prompting that
you yourself haven't chosen or created.
And here it's worth
noticing Kant's specially demanding idea of freedom.
What way of acting?
How can my will be determined, if not by
the promptings of nature or my
hunger or my appetite or my desires?
Kant's answer, to act freely is to act autonomously.
And to act autonomously is to act
according to a law that I give myself,
not according
to the physical laws of nature or
to the laws of cause and effect,
which include my desire to eat or to drink or
choose this food in a restaurant over that.
Now, what is the opposite?
What is the opposite of autonomy?
For Kant, he invents a special
term to describe the opposite of autonomy.
Heteronomy is the opposite of autonomy.
When I act
heteronymously, I'm acting according to an inclination
or a desire that I haven't chosen for myself.
So freedom as autonomy
is the specially stringent idea that Kant insists on.
Now, why is autonomy
the opposite of acting heteronymously or
according to the dictates of nature?
Kant's point is that nature is governed by laws,
laws of cause and effect, for example.
Suppose you drop a billiard ball.
It falls to the ground.
We wouldn't say the billiard ball is acting freely.
Why not?
It's acting according to the law of nature,
according to the laws
of cause and effect, the law of gravity.
And just as he has an
unusually demanding and stringent conception of freedom,
freedom as autonomy, he also
has a demanding conception of morality.
To act freely is not to choose
the best means to a given end.
It's to choose the end itself for its own
sake.
And that's something
that human beings can do
and that billiard balls can't.
Insofar as we act on inclination or pursue pleasure,
we act as means to the
realization of ends given outside us.
We are instruments rather than authors
of the purposes
we pursue.
That's
the heteronymous determination of the will.
On the other hand, insofar as we act autonomously,
according to a law we give ourselves,
we do something for its own
sake, as an end in itself.
When we act autonomously,
we cease to be instruments to purposes given outside us.
We become,
or we can come to think of ourselves,
as ends in ourselves.
This capacity to act freely,
Kant tells us, is what
gives human life its special dignity.
Respecting human dignity means regarding
persons not just as means,
but also as ends in themselves.
And this is why it's wrong to use
people for the sake of other people's well-being
or happiness.
This is the real reason,
Kant says, that utilitarianism goes wrong.
This is the reason it's important
to respect the dignity of persons
and to uphold their rights.
So even if there are cases,
remember, John Stuart Mill said, well,
in the long run, if we uphold
justice and respect the dignity of persons,
we will maximize human happiness.
What would Kant's answer be to that?
What would his answer be?
Even if that were true, even
if the calculus worked out that way,
even if you shouldn't throw the Christians to the lions,
because in the long run, fear
will spread, the overall utility will decline,
the utilitarian would be upholding justice
and rights and respect for persons
for the wrong reason, for a purely contingent reason,
for an instrumental
reason.
It would still be using people,
even where the calculus works out
for the best in the long run,
it would still be using people as means
rather than respecting them as ends in themselves.
So that's Kant's idea of freedom is autonomy.
And you can begin to see how
it's connected to his idea of morality.
But we still have to answer one more question.
What gives an act its
moral worth in the first place?
If it can't be directed
at utility or satisfying wants and desires,
what gives an action its moral worth?
This leads us from Kant's demanding idea
of freedom to his demanding idea of morality.
What does Kant say?
What makes an action morally worthy
consists not in the consequences or
in the results that flow from it.
What makes an action morally worthy has to do
with the motive,
with the quality of the will, with the intention
for which the act is done.
What matters is the motive.
And the motive must be of a certain kind.
So the moral worth of an action
depends on the motive for which it's done.
And the important thing is that the person
do the right thing for the right reason.
A good will isn't good because of
what it affects or accomplishes, Kant writes.
It's good in itself.
Even if by its utmost
effort, the good will accomplishes nothing,
it would still shine like
a jewel for its own sake
as something which has its full value in itself.
And so for any action to be morally good,
it's not enough that it
should conform to the moral law.
It must also be done for
the sake of the moral law.
The idea is that the motive
that confers the moral worth on an action.
And the only kind of motive that
can confirm moral worth on an action
is the motive of duty.
Well, what's the opposite of doing something out
of a sense of duty because it's right?
Well, for Kant, the opposite would be all
of those motives having to do with our inclinations.
And inclinations refer to all of our
desires, all of our contingently given
wants, preferences, impulses, and the like.
Only actions done for the sake of
the moral law, for the sake of duty,
only these actions have moral worth.
Now I want to see
what you think about this idea,
but first let's consider a few examples.
Kant begins with an example of a shopkeeper.
He wants to bring out the idea that,
by the intuition, and make plausible the idea
that what confers moral worth on an action
is that it be done because it's right.
He says, suppose there's a shopkeeper,
and an inexperienced customer comes in.
The shopkeeper knows that he could
give the customer the wrong change,
could shortchange the customer and get away with it.
At least that customer wouldn't know.
But the shopkeeper knows that he's not the one
who's going to give the customer the wrong change.
He nonetheless says, well, if I shortchange this customer,
word may get out, my reputation would
be damaged, and I would lose business.
So I won't shortchange this customer.
The shopkeeper does nothing wrong.
He gives the correct change.
But does his action have moral worth?
Kant says no.
It doesn't have moral worth, because
the shopkeeper only did the right thing
for the wrong reason, out of self-interest.
That's a pretty straightforward case.
Then he takes another case, the case of suicide.
He says we have a duty to preserve ourselves.
Now, for most people who
love life, we have multiple reasons.
For not taking our own lives.
So the only way we can really tell,
the only way we can isolate the operative motive
for someone who doesn't take his or her life,
is to think, to imagine someone who's miserable.
And who, despite
having an absolutely miserable life,
nonetheless,
recognizes the duty to preserve oneself,
and so does not commit suicide.
That's the force of the example,
is to bring out the motive that matters.
And the motive that matters for morality is
doing the right thing for the sake of duty.
Let me just give you
a couple of other examples.
The Better Business Bureau.
What's their slogan?
The slogan of the Better Business Bureau?
Honesty is the best policy.
It's also the most profitable.
This is the Better Business Bureau's
full-page ad in the New York Times.
Honesty.
It's as important as any other asset.
Because a business that deals
in truth, openness, and fair value,
cannot help but do well.
Come join us and profit from it.
What would Kant say about the moral worth
of the honest dealings of
members of the Better Business Bureau?
What would he say?
That here's a perfect example,
that if this is the reason that
these companies deal honestly with their customers,
their action lacks moral worth.
This is Kant's point.
A couple of years ago at the University of Maryland,
there was a problem with cheating.
And so they initiated an honor system.
And they created a program with local merchants
that if you signed the honor
pledge, a pledge not to cheat,
you would get discounts of
10 to 25% at local shops.
Well, what would you think of someone
motivated to uphold an honor
code with the hope of discounts?
It's the same as Kant's shopkeeper.
The point is, what matters
is the quality of the will,
the character of the motive,
and the relevant motive to morality
can only be the motive of
duty, not the motive of inclination.
And when I act out of duty,
when I resist as my motive for acting,
inclinations or self-interest, even sympathy and altruism,
only then am I acting freely,
only then am I acting autonomously.
Only then is my will not
determined or governed by external considerations.
That's the link between Kant's idea of freedom
and of morality.
Now, I want to pause here to
see if all of this is clear,
or if you have some questions or puzzles.
They can be questions of
clarification, or they can be challenges.
If you want to challenge this idea
that only the motive of duty
confers moral worth on the action.
What do you think? Yes.
Yeah, I actually have two questions of clarification.
The first is, there seems to be an
aspect of this that makes it sort of
self-defeating in that once you're
conscious of what morality is,
you can sort of alter your
motive to achieve that end of morality.
And secondly... Give me an example
of what you have in mind.
The shopkeeper example, if he decides
that he wants to give the person
the money to do the right thing, and
he decides that's his motive to do so,
because he wants to be moral,
then isn't that sort of defeating,
trying to... Isn't that sort of
defeating the purity of his action?
If morality is determined by his motive,
his motive is then to act morally.
So you're imagining a case not
of the purely selfish calculating shopkeeper,
but of one who says, well,
he may consider shortchanging the customer,
but then he says, not, well,
my reputation might suffer if word gets
out, but instead he says, actually, I
would like to be the kind of honest
person who gives the right change
to customers simply because it's the right
thing to do. Or simply
because I want to be moral.
Because I want to be moral.
I want to be a good person.
And so I'm going to conform all
of my actions to what morality requires.
A little point. It's a good question.
Kant does acknowledge, you're pressing
Kant on an important point here,
Kant does say there has to be
some incentive to obey the moral law.
It can't be a self-interested incentive
that would defeat it by definition.
So he speaks of a different kind of incentive
and inclination. He speaks of reverence for the moral law.
So if that shopkeeper says,
I want to develop
a reverence for the moral law,
and so I'm going to do the right thing,
then I think he's there.
He's there as far as Kant's concerned,
because he's formed his motive, his will,
is conforming
to the moral law once
he sees the importance of it.
So it would count. It would count.
All right. And then secondly, very quickly,
what stops morality from becoming
completely objective in this point?
What stops morality from becoming completely subjective?
Like how can if there's if
morally is if morality is completely determined
by your morals, then how can you
apply this or how can it be enforced?
That's also a great question.
What's your name?
My name is Amadi.
Amadi.
All right.
If acting morally means acting according
to a moral law out of duty,
and if it's also to act
freely in the sense of autonomously,
it must mean that I'm acting according
to a law that I give myself.
That's what it means to act autonomously.
Amadi is right about that.
But that does raise a really interesting question.
If acting autonomously means acting according
to a law I give myself,
that's how I escape the chain of
cause and effect and the laws of nature.
What's to guarantee
that the law I give myself
when I'm acting out of duty is the same
as the law that Amadi is giving him?
What's to guarantee that the law I give myself
is the same as the
law that Amadi is giving himself
and that each of you gives yourselves?
Well, here's the question.
How many moral laws, from Kant's point
of view, are there in this room?
Are there a thousand or is there one?
He thinks there's one, which in a
way does go back to this question.
All right. What is the moral law?
What does it tell us?
So what guarantees?
It sounds like it to act autonomously
is to act according to one's conscience,
according to a law one gives oneself.
But what guarantees that if we all exercise our reason,
we will come up with
one and the same moral law?
That's what Amadi wants to know.
Here's Kant's answer.
The reason that leads us,
to the law we give ourselves as autonomous beings,
is a reason,
it's a kind of practical reason
that we share as human beings.
It's not idiosyncratic.
The reason we need to respect the dignity of persons
is that we're all rational beings.
We all have the capacity for reason.
And it's the exercise of that capacity for reason,
which exists undifferentiated in all of us,
that makes us worthy of dignity, all of us.
And since it's the same capacity for reason,
unqualified by particular
autobiographies and life circumstances,
it's the same universal capacity for reason
that delivers the moral law.
It turns out that to act autonomously
is to act according to a law we give ourselves,
exercising our reason,
but it's the reason we
share with everyone as rational beings,
not the particular reasons we have given our upbringings,
our particular values, our particular interests.
It's pure practical reason in Kant's terms,
which legislates
a priori, regardless of any
particular contingent or empirical ends.
Well, what moral law would that kind of reason deliver?
What is its content?
To answer that question,
you have to read the groundwork,
and we'll continue with that question next time.
We'll continue with that question next time.
Thank you.
Thank you, all.
For Kant, morally speaking, suicide
is on a par with murder.
It's on a par with murder because what we violate
when we take a life,
when we take someone's life, ours or somebody else's,
we use that person,
we use a rational being,
we use humanity as a means,
And so we fail to respect humanity as an end.
Today we turn back to Kant before we do...
Remember, this is the week by the end of which
all of you will basically get
Kant, figure out what he's up to.
You're laughing. No, it will happen.
Kant's groundwork is about two big questions.
First, what is the supreme principle of morality?
Second, how is freedom possible?
Two big questions.
Now, one way of making your
way through this dense philosophical book
is to bear in mind a set of
oppositions or contrasts or dualisms that are related.
Today I'd like to talk about them.
Today we're going to answer the question,
what, according to Kant, is
the supreme principle of morality?
And in answering that question, in working our
way up to Kant's answer to that question,
it will help to bear in mind
three contrasts or dualisms that Kant sets out.
The first, you'll remember,
had to do with the
motive according to which we act.
And according to Kant, only one
kind of motive is consistent with morality.
The motive of duty.
Doing the right thing for the right reason.
What other kind of motives are there?
Kant sums them up in the category of inclination.
Every time the motive for what we do is to
satisfy a desire or a preference that we may have
to pursue some interest, we're acting out of inclination.
Now, let me pause to see if,
in thinking about the question of
the motive of duty, the good will,
see if any of you has a
question about that much of Kant's claim.
Or is everybody happy with this distinction?
What do you think?
Go ahead.
When you make that distinction between duty and inclination,
is there ever any moral action, ever?
I mean, you could always, kind of,
probably find some selfish motive, can't you?
Maybe very often people do
have self-interested motives when they act.
Kant wouldn't dispute that.
But what Kant is saying is
that insofar as we act morally,
that is, insofar as our actions have moral worth,
what confers moral worth is precisely
our capacity to rise above
self-interest and prudence and inclination
and to act out of duty.
Some years ago I read about a spelling bee.
And there was a young man who
was declared the winner of the spelling bee.
A kid named Andrew, 13 years old.
The winning word,
the word that he was able to spell,
was echolalia.
Does anyone know what echolalia is?
What?
It's not some type of flower, no.
It means the tendency to repeat, as in echo,
to repeat what you've heard.
Anyhow, he misspelled it, actually.
But the judges misheard him.
They thought he had spelled it correctly
and awarded him the championship
of the national spelling bee.
And he went to the judges afterward and said,
actually, I misspelled it.
I don't deserve the prize.
And he was regarded as a moral hero,
and he was written up in the New York Times,
Miss Speller is a spelling bee hero.
There's Andrew.
With his proud mother.
And when he was interviewed afterwards,
listen to this,
when he was interviewed afterwards,
he said, quote,
the judges said I had a lot of integrity.
But then he added that
part of his motive was, quote,
I didn't want to feel like a slime.
I had to think about it.
He was a very, very smart person.
And he got to say it.
And I'm a big fan of his words.
I just don't want to hear his thing.
All right.
What would Kant say?
Go ahead.
I guess it would depend on whether or not
that was a marginal reason or the predominant reason
in whether or not in why he decided to confess
that he didn't actually spell the word correctly.
Good.
And what's your name?
Vosko.
That's very interesting.
Is there anyone else who has a view about this?
Does this show that Kant is a liberal?
I think, I think it does.
I think he's a good answer.
I think, I think he's a good answer.
That's very interesting. Is there anyone
else who has a view about this?
Does this show that Kant's
principle is too stringent, too demanding?
What would Kant say about this? Yes.
I think that Kant actually says that it is the pure
motivation that comes out of duty which gives the action moral growth.
So it's like, for example, in this
case, he might have more than one motive.
He might have the motive of not feeling like a slime, and he might
have the motive of doing the right thing in and of itself, out of duty.
And so while there's more than one motivation going on there, it does not mean
that the action is devoid of moral worth just because he has one other motive.
So because the motive which involves duty
is what gives it the moral growth.
Good. And what's your name? Judith.
Well, Judith, I think that your...
Your account actually is true to Kant.
It's fine to have sentiments and feelings that support doing
the right thing, provided they don't provide the reason for acting.
So I think Judith actually has mounted a pretty good defense
of Kant on this question of the motive of duty. Thank you.
Now, let's go back to the three contrasts.
It's the motive of duty.
It's clear at least what Kant means when he says that for an action to
have moral worth, it must be done for the sake of duty, not out of inclination.
But as we began to see last time, there's a connection between
Kant's stringent notion of morality and his specially demanding understanding of freedom.
And that leads us to the second contrast.
The link between morality and freedom.
The second contrast describes two different
ways that my will can be determined.
Autonomously and heteronymously.
And according to Kant, I'm only free when
my will is determined autonomously, which means what?
According to a law that I give myself.
We must be capable, if we're capable of freedom as autonomy, we must be capable of acting according
not to a law that's given or imposed on us, but according to a law we give ourselves.
But where could such a law come from?
A law that we give ourselves?
Reason.
If reason determines my will,
then the will becomes the power to choose independent
of the dictates of nature or inclination or circumstance.
So, connected with Kant's demanding notions of morality
and freedom is a specially demanding notion of reason.
Well, how can reason determine the will?
There are two ways.
And this leads to the third contrast.
Kant says there are two different commands of reason.
And a command of reason, Kant calls an imperative.
An imperative is simply an ought.
One kind of imperative, perhaps the
most familiar kind, is a hypothetical imperative.
Hypothetical imperatives use instrumental reason.
If you want X, then do Y.
It means ends reasoning.
If you want a good business
reputation, then don't shortchange your customers.
Word may get out.
That's a hypothetical imperative.
If the action would be good solely as
a means to something else, Kant writes the imperative,
is hypothetical.
If the action is represented as good in itself,
and therefore as necessary for a
will which of itself accords with reason,
then the imperative is categorical.
That's the difference between a
categorical imperative and a hypothetical one.
A categorical imperative commands categorically.
Which just means without reference to
or dependence on any further purpose.
And so you see the
connection among these three parallel contrasts.
To be free in the sense of autonomous requires
that I act not out of a hypothetical imperative,
but out of a categorical imperative.
And so you see by these
three contrasts, Kant reasons his way,
brings us up to his
derivation of the categorical imperative.
Well, this leaves us one big question.
What is the categorical imperative?
What is the supreme principle of morality?
What does it command of us?
Kant gives three versions, three formulations,
of the categorical imperative.
I want to mention two, and
then see what you think of them.
The first version, the first formula,
he calls the formula of the universal law.
Act only on that maxim,
whereby you can at the same time
will that it should become a universal law.
And by maxim, what does Kant mean?
He means,
a rule that explains the reason for what you're doing.
A principle.
For example, promise keeping.
Suppose I need money, I need a hundred dollars,
desperately.
And I know I can't pay it back anytime soon.
I come to you and make
you a promise, a false promise,
one I know I can't keep.
Please give me a hundred dollars today,
lend me the money, I will repay you next week.
Is that consistent
with the categorical imperative, that false promise?
Kant says, no.
And the test, the way we can determine
that the false promise is at
odds with the categorical imperative is,
try to universalize it.
Universalize the maxim upon which you're about to act.
If everybody made false promises when they needed money,
then nobody would believe those promises,
there would be no such thing as a promise,
and so there would be a contradiction.
The maxim universalized would undermine itself.
That's the test.
That's how we can know
that the false promise is wrong.
Well, what about the formula of the universal law?
You find it persuasive?
What do you think?
Go ahead.
I have a question about the difference between
categoricalism and a hypothesis that
if you're going to act...
Between categorical and hypothetical...
Hypothetical, yeah.
Imperatives.
Right.
If you're going to act with a categorical imperative
so that the maxim doesn't undermine itself,
it sounds like I am going
to do X because I want Y.
I am going to not lie in dire need
because I want the world to function
in such a way that promises are kept.
I don't want to liquidate the practice of promises.
Right.
It sounds like justifying...
Justifying a means by an ends.
It seems like an instance
of consequentialist reasoning, you're saying.
Right.
And what's your name?
Tim.
Well, Tim, John Stuart Mill agreed with you.
He made this criticism of Kant.
He said, if I universalize the maxim and find
that the whole practice of promise
keeping would be destroyed if universalized,
I must be appealing somehow to consequences.
Right.
If that's the reason not to tell a false promise.
So John Stuart Mill agreed with that criticism against Kant.
But John Stuart Mill was wrong.
You're in good company, though.
You're in good company, Tim.
Kant is often read, as Tim just read him,
as appealing to consequences.
The world would be worse off if everybody lied
because then no one could rely on anybody else's word.
Therefore, you shouldn't lie.
That's not what Kant is saying exactly.
Although it's easy to interpret him as saying that.
I think what he's saying
is that this is the test.
This is the test of whether the maxim corresponds
with the categorical imperative.
It isn't exactly the reason.
It's not the reason.
The reason you should universalize to test your maxim
is to see whether you are privileging your particular needs
and desires over everybody else's.
It's a way of pointing to this feature,
this demand of the categorical imperative,
that the reasons for your actions shouldn't depend
for their justification on your interests,
your needs, your special circumstances
being more important than somebody else's.
That, I think, is the moral intuition
lying behind the universalization.
That's the moral test.
So let me spell out the second,
Kant's second version of the categorical imperative,
perhaps in a way that's more intuitively accessible
than the formula of universal law.
It's the formula of humanity as an end.
Kant introduces the second version
of the categorical imperative
with the following line of argument.
We can't base the categorical imperative
on any particular interest, purposes, or ends,
because then it would be only relative
to the person whose ends they were.
But suppose there were something
whose existence has in itself an absolute value,
an end in itself.
Then in it, and in it alone,
would there be the ground
of a possible categorical imperative?
Well, what is there that we can think of
as having its end in itself?
Kant's answer is this.
I say that man, and in general,
every rational being,
exists as an end in himself,
not merely as a means for arbitrary use
by this or that will.
And here Kant distinguishes
between persons on the one hand
and things on the other.
Rational beings are persons.
They don't just have a relative value for us,
but if anything has,
they have an absolute value,
an intrinsic value.
That is, rational beings have dignity.
They're worthy of reverence and respect.
This line of reasoning leads Kant
to the second formulation
of the categorical imperative,
which is this.
Act in such a way
that you always treat humanity,
whether in your own person
or in the person of any other,
never simply as a means,
but always at the same time as an end.
So that's the formula
of humanity as an end.
The idea that human beings,
as rational beings,
are ends in themselves,
not open to use,
merely as a means.
When I make a false promise to you,
I'm using you as a means
to my ends,
to my desire for the hundred dollars.
And so I'm failing to respect you.
I'm failing to respect your dignity.
I'm manipulating you.
Now consider the example
of the duty against suicide.
Murder and suicide
are at odds with the categorical imperative.
Why?
If I murder someone,
I'm taking their life for some purpose,
either because I'm a hired killer,
or I'm in the throes
of some great anger or passion.
Well, I have some interest,
some purpose that's particular
for the sake of which I'm using them
as a means.
Murder violates
the categorical imperative.
For Kant, morally speaking,
suicide is on a par with murder.
It's on a par with murder
because what we violate
when we take a life,
when we take someone's life,
ours or somebody else's,
we use that person,
we use a rational being,
we use humanity as a means,
and so we fail to respect humanity
as an end.
And that capacity for reason,
that humanity
that commands respect,
that is the ground of dignity,
that humanity,
that capacity for reason,
resides undifferentiated
in all of us.
And so I violate that dignity
in my own person
if I commit suicide,
and in murder
if I take somebody else's life.
From a moral point of view,
they're the same.
And the reason they're the same
has to do with the universal character
and ground of the moral law.
The reason that we have to respect
the dignity of other people
has not to do with anything
in particular about them.
And so respect, Kantian respect,
is unlike love in this way.
It's unlike sympathy.
It's unlike solidarity
or fellow feeling or altruism.
Because love and those other
particular virtues or reasons
for caring about other people
have to do with who they are
in particular.
But respect for Kant,
respect is respect for humanity
which is universal,
for a rational capacity
which is universal.
And that's why violating it
in my own case
is as objectionable
as violating it
in the case of any other.
Questions or objections?
Go ahead.
I guess I'm somewhat worried
about Kant's statement
that you cannot use a person
as a means because every person
is an end in and of themselves.
Because it seems that
every day in order to get
something accomplished
for that day,
I must use myself as a means
to some end.
And I must use the people around me
as a means to some end as well.
For instance, suppose that
I want to do well in a class
and I have to write a paper.
I have to use myself as a means
to write the paper.
Suppose I want to buy something.
Food.
I must go to the store
and use the person
working behind the counter
as a means for me
to purchase my food.
Right.
That's true.
You do.
What's your name?
Patrick.
Patrick, you're not doing
anything wrong.
You're not violating
the categorical imperative
when you use other people
as means.
That's not objectionable
provided
when we deal with other people
for the sake of advancing
our projects and purposes
and interests,
which we all do,
provided we treat them
in a way that is consistent
with respect for their dignity.
And what it means to respect them
is given by the categorical imperative.
Are you persuaded?
Do you think that Kant has given
a compelling account,
a persuasive account,
of the supreme principle of morality?
Reread the groundwork
and we'll try to answer
that question.
We'll answer that question
next time.
Thank you.
Don't miss the chance
to interact online
with other viewers of Justice.
Join the conversation.
Take a pop quiz.
Watch lectures you've missed
and learn a lot more.
Visit JusticeHarvard.org.
It's the right thing to do.
Thank you.
Funding for this program is provided by
Additional funding provided by